Guide to the Adele Buchalter Scrapbooks circa 1866-1981 MS 86
New-York Historical Society
Adele Buchalter scrapbooks
circa 1866-1981
New-York Historical Society
Buchalter, Adele, 1899-1991
MS 86
3.5 Linear feet in 14 flat boxes (29 volumes)
The collection holds 29 scrapbooks compiled by New Yorker Adele Buchalter (1899-1991). Comprised primarily of photographs, the albums trace Buchalter's life from infancy through her move at age 80 to a retirement community. Subjects include, among others, Buchalter's school years at Horace Mann School for Girls and Vassar College, volunteer service at the start of World War I, her career in retail mostly as a buyer/purchasing agent, her family history (which includes 19th century Jewish immigrants from Germany), and extensive travels in the 1970s.
Arrangement
The albums are presented in the order as numbered on their labels. The order is roughly chronological.
Biographical / Historical
Adele Buchalter (nee Lowinson) was born in New York City in 1899 to Frieda and Louis Lowinson. This collection provides some of her family ancestry, going back to her great-grandfather, Leon Sternberger, who was born in Bavaria in 1819. Sternberger, a Jewish cantor, immigrated to the United States in 1849 and later became cantor at Temple Beth El in Manhattan. Other members of Buchalter's extended family were also Jewish immigrants from Germany in the 19th century.
Adele Lowinson attended Horace Mann School for Girls, graduating in 1916. She then attended Vassar College, where she met Lieutenant Benjamin Buchalter of the U.S. Navy in 1917 as he passed through New York City during his military service in World War I. Adele married Buchalter in 1918. She continued her education at Vassar for a time, but apparently did not graduate, though she identified with her Class of 1920 through her life. She would eventually finish her studies, earning a B.A. in 1952 from the University of California at Berkeley.
Adele and Benjamin had two sons, Benjamin Jr. (born 1921) and Lloyd Arthur (born 1923). Tragically, Adele's husband died of tuberculosis in 1925 and Adele raised her sons as a single mother, likely with the help of her parents. To support the family, Adele entered the workforce about 1926, working as a salesperson and eventually as a buyer, or purchasing agent, in the retail field, specifically in the area of infant and children's wear. Along the way, she also seems to have been involved with design work of marketing materials and of children's games. She also was active in the buyers' trade association.
By 1970, Buchalter was working for the New York State Department of Labor as an Employment Counselor when, at age 70, she was required by law to retire from state employment. At that time she became an instructor of economics for the Henry George School of Social Science in New York. In that capacity she traveled to Calgary in Alberta, Canada, for a conference. She was so entranced with Calgary that, shortly after in 1972, she bought a house there and left New York. Through the 1970s, she joined tour groups to travel extensively in Europe, Asia, and elsewhere. In 1979, she sold her home in Calgary and moved to Washington Square, a retirement community in Hinsdale, Illinois. Adele Buchalter died in 1991.
(The above note was gleaned from documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Some of the documents (e.g. letters, cards, brochures, multi-page notes) can only be fully read when removed from the scrapbooks' page enclosures, and some of these can only be removed with some difficulty. Patrons wishing to access such documents need to bring them to the attention of the reference librarian for assessment and determination of proper handling.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lloyd Buchalter, 2003.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 29 scrapbooks compiled by Adele Buchalter documenting the arc of her life from infancy in 1899 to her life in a retirement community in 1981, with particular emphasis on her connections with family and friends, aspects of her career, and extensive travel later in life. The first album centers on Buchalter's family history, including ancestors and descendants from her extended family.
The albums principally hold photographs, which are typically captioned, at least collectively and sufficiently to provide context and identification of individuals and places. There are also a variety of other document types; depending on the subject matter these include event programs, certificates, dance cards, invitations, letters, newspaper clippings, postcards, artwork (from children and adults), travel itineraries and brochures, and more. Glimpses of Buchalter's career in retail and as a purchasing agent, and later as an instructor of economics, are found in some of the scrapbooks in the form of business correspondence, compensation slips, acknowledgements of her work, articles she wrote, and other material. The later volumes, which emphasize travel, often include Buchalter's circular letters to her friends and family summarizing her travels or other activities for a given year.
The container list below provides a sense of the subject content of each volume as perceived by the processing archivist from a skim of each. The title used for the album is that found on the album's label, presumably given by Buchalter. Post-it notes and other notations found throughout the volumes were likely made by family members and are suggestive that some portions were scanned before donation to N-YHS.
Jews -- New York (State) -- New York.; Purchasing agents.; Retail trade -- United States.; Voyages and travels -- Albums (books); Women -- New York (State) -- New York.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Civilian relief.; Albums (books); Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Printed ephemera.; Vassar College
- Volume 1. "Family History", circa 1866-1968 (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  A page of this volume holds at least a partial genealogy of the 4 or 5 generations beginning with Buchalter's maternal great-grandfather, Leon Sternberger. The volume includes photographs of many of the people identified in the genealogy and also many later generations and others in Buchalter's extended family. Surnames include Lewinson, Lowinson, Ash, Latz, Sternberger, and many others.
- Volume 2. "AB Childhood", 1899-circa 1913 (Offsite-box 1)
  The volume begins with a photo of Adele Buchalter (then Adele Lowinson) as an infant and spans her childhood years. Includes photos taken with her "first camera" a "Box Brownie #2." There are photos of her home (301 West 108th Street), travel to Washington D.C., the family's first car, summer vacation in New Jersey (along the Morris Canal), Hudson-Fulton Celebration Parade, school sports (e.g., Horace Mann football), a trip to the Panama Canal, and more. Documents include artwork, report cards, souvenir maps, handbooks, a diary entry, and schoolwork.
- Volume 3. "AB High School", 1913-1972 (Offsite-box 2)
  This volume includes Lowinson/Buchalter's summers at Highland Nature Club in South Naples, Maine, with photographs and other documents related to camp activities (e.g. hiking, sports, including basketball for which Adele was manager of the camp team, etc.), facilities, and friends. Also included are clippings, photographs (classmates, teachers, facilities, events, etc.), commencement program, dance card, etc. from her years at Horace Mann School for Girls. The core date range is 1913-16, but there are additional, later documents to 1972.
- Volume 4. "Vassar [crossed out]; WWI", 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 2)
  This volume primarily includes Buchalter's early years at Vassar College and the impact of the beginning of World War I. The album holds an envelope labeled "How it all began!!"; this includes a letter from a friend arranging a blind date for Adele with a Navy sailor passing through New York. That sailor is Benjamin Buchalter who Adele marries the following year. (Please consult with the reference librarian on the removal of this and other letters from the scrapbook enclosures.) Vassar documents include photographs of the campus, classmates, her dorm (Davison House), geology field trip, and more. Buchalter's involvement on the WWI homefront, as well as that of her friends and family, is represented by, among other documents, a certificate of membership in the Patriotic Service League (1917), and photos of her relatives in uniform, including ambulance driver Elsie Gutmam. There is a photo of Benjamin Buchalter and his Navy calling card, and the announcement of their engagement (1918).
- Volume 5. "AB Gets Married", 1909, 1918, 1970s (Offsite-box 3)
  The album is a copy of "The House that Jack Built: A Wedding Book," copyright 1909 by Paul Elper & Company. Includes photos, clippings, and guest and gift lists. At the back of the album are color snapshots of another wedding, circa 1970s. Also at the back are various greeting cards and letters to Buchalter dating from the 1970s.
- Volume 6. "Vassar & 50th Reunion," 1918-1920, 1918-1920, 1970, 1980 (Offsite-box 3)
  This volume covers Buchalter's later years at Vassar. Photos include the "Vassar Farmerettes who took the place of men who were called to duty in W.W.1". There is a profile snapshot of Edna St. Vincent Millay, prom photos, class plays, commencement documents for Buchalter's Class of 1920, etc. Later material includes a 1970 reunion program and some other material from that year and documents from the 1980 reunion, including notes by Buchalter apparently delivered to the reunion regarding her travels in Asia.
- Volume 7. "LAB [Lloyd Arthur Buchalter] 2-19-23", 1923-1925 (Offsite-box 3)
  The album is a "Baby's Journal" with decorations/illustrations by Blanche Fisher Wright, published by the Universal Press. Given to Buchalter to document her second child, Lloyd Arthur Buchalter (sometimes called "Buddy"), born February 19, 1923. Includes artwork, notes, and photographs.
- Volume 8. "Father dies. The boys grow up. Mother goes to work", 1925-1946 (Offsite-box 4)
  The album records that Buchalter's husband, Benjamin, died in June 1926 of "military tuberculosis." From there, the volume traces two main themes: the growth of the Buchalters two sons, Benjamin Jr and Lloyd, and Adele's career into the mid-1940s. Includes photographs of the boys growing to become young men, at camp, at home (600 West End Ave), etc. Adele's career in sales, retail, and as a purchasing agent for various companies is indicated through marketing materials for press clipping services, compensation slips from Macy's, samples of marketing materials, letter from Ullman Manufacturing Company regarding royalties to be paid to Adele for her design of the Alice in Wonderland game (marketed beginning 1934), and other documents. The scrapbook also includes documentation of the 99th birthday party and death shortly after of Adele's grandfather, Emanuel Lowinson.
- Volume 9. "AB works, gets BA", 1943-1952 (Offsite-box 4)
  This volume opens with the marriage (1943) of Benjamin, Jr. to Bertha Maier. It continues to trace Adele's career, including becoming a children's wear buyer for Julius Gutman & Co. and moving to Baltimore to work at The Hub. Documents indicate that she was active in the Infant's and Children's Wear Buyers' Association, and these include an unattributed article written by her in the association's magazine in support of the need for buyers. Tickets, a songbook, snapshots from a Shibe Park rally, and a reception invitation suggest she was a Henry A. Wallace supporter in 1948, and that she may have attended a dinner and reception with Wallace and Paul Robeson. There are travel photos and souvenirs from Quebec, Ausable Chasm, and other places in upper New York State and the surrounding area. Finally, there is documentation from the University of California at Berkeley where Buchalter briefly matriculated to earn a B.A. in 1952 (degree certificate in scrapbook).
- Volume 10. "Little Adele," 1941-1976 (Offsite-box 5)
  This volume traces Buchalter's niece, Adele Paulette Lowinson, from birth (1941) to about 1959 and her wedding to James Russell Jones. Other children and families are similarly traced across the decades in the album. These include, among others, Adele Kish, born 1941 and through her marriage to Robert Bidwell Suydam in 1960 and then their childen, ending about 1976; and the Hackes, Andersons, Donn/Burtons, Gunthers, and Buddas (who Buchalter visits in London in 1976).
- Volume 11. "Family", 1953-1969 (Offsite-box 5)
  This volume includes photos and other documents concerning Buchalter's son Lloyd's marriage (1953) to Dorothy Joyce Cecire. For the most part the album includes photos and travel souvenirs of Buchalter visits to family and friends in San Francisco, Long Island, Masachusetts, Virginia, Miami/Florida, etc.
- Volume 12. "In Memoriam: Frieda and Louis Lowinson", 1917-1970 (Offsite-box 6)
  This volume includes, among other documents, photographs, certificates (including for Jewish philanthropic matters), clippings, artwork (by Frieda), and letters in relation to Adele's parents, Frieda (1873-1970) and Louis (1874-1952), and their son, Ralph.
- Volume 13. "Hawaii", 1967, 1974 (Offsite-box 6)
- Volume 14. "Ireland", 1968 (Offsite-box 7)
- Volume 15. "Florida, AB Retires", 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 7)
  This volume includes Buchalter's travels to Florida (1968), a visit to friends in Denver (1969), and some snapshots of the construction of Madison Square Garden (1969). Her continued career is glimpsed as, at age 70 in 1969, documents indicate she is legally required to retire from her position as Employent Counselor working for the New York State Department of Labor. Documents here indicate Buchalter continuing to work as an instructor in economics at the Henry George School of Social Science (50 East 69th St, NYC), beginning in 1969-70.
- Volume 16. "1st Trip to Canada", 1970 (Offsite-box 8)
  The volume begins in Calgary with attendance and panel participation at the 26th Annual Conference of the Henry George Schools of North America (July 7-12), then documents further travels in Alberta and British Columbia. See Volume 19 for letter from Buchalter indicating how she was so taken with Calgary on this trip that she chose to purchase a home and move here in 1972.
- Volume 17. "Europe", 1971 (Offsite-box 8)
  This volume documents Buchalter's travels with the South Street Seaport Museum's Maritime Europe Tour (London, Paris, Chartres). Continues in volume 18.
- Volume 18. "England, Holland", 1971 (Offsite-box 9)
  This volume continues from volume 17.
- Volume 19. "Move to Calgary", 1971-1980 (Offsite-box 9)
  This volume primarily covers the years 1972-75 with Adele's farewell to New York City, photographs of her new home in Calgary, travels in the region of her new home, and visitors. Some later dated material from 1977-80 is in the album, including the death of her niece Adele's husband, James R. Jones (1977).
- Volume 20. "Asia", 1973 (Offsite-box 10)
  One of three scrapbooks covering her trip of February-April, 1973; see also volumes 21 and 22. (See Adele's letter summarizing her trip in volume 21. A copy is also in volume 22). This volume includes Thailand, Indonesia, Bali, Singapore, Hong Kong, Taiwan.
- Volume 21. "Japan", 1973 (Offsite-box 10)
  One of three scrapbooks covering her trip of February-April, 1973; see also volumes 20 and 22. Includes a letter from Adele to family and friends summarizing her trip.
- Volume 22. "N.Z. [New Zealand] and Australia", 1973 (Offsite-box 11)
  One of three scrapbooks covering her trip of February-April, 1973; see also volumes 20 and 21.
- Volume 23. "South Seas", 1974 (Offsite-box 11)
- Volume 24. "South America", 1975 (Offsite-box 12)
  This volume includes travel to Columbia (Bogota), Peru (Lima, Cuzco, Machu Picchu, etc.), Bolivia (La Paz), Argentina (Buenos Aires, Rio de Janeiro), Brazil (Sao Paulo, etc.).
- Volume 25. "Canada and Family", 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 12)
  This volume includes Buchalter's travels in Alberta, visits from friends and family, and her departure from her Calgary home for a retirement community in Hinsdale, Ilinois.
- Volume 26. "Calgary" [England, Alaska, Yukon], 1977 (Offsite-box 13)
  Though labeled as "Calgary," this album includes travel to England (mostly Stratford-on-Avon) and to Canada's Northwest Territories, Alaska, and the Yukon.
- Volume 27. "Africa" [Kenya], 1977 (Offsite-box 13)
- Volume 28. "Europe", 1979 (Offsite-box 14)
  This volume includes travel to Paris, England, and Scotland.
- Volume 29. "Hinsdale, Illinois", 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 14)
  This volume documents Buchalter's move to Washington Square, a retirement community near Chicago; her 80th birthday; and various organizations and activities she was engaged with in Hinsdale, closing in 1981.